<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>News on Infergo — Go programs that learn</title>
    <link>http://infergo.org/news/</link>
    <description>Recent content in News on Infergo — Go programs that learn</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 00:43:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://infergo.org/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>infergo v0.7.0</title>
      <link>http://infergo.org/news/v0.7.0/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 00:43:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://infergo.org/news/v0.7.0/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Infergo v0.7.0 is &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/dtolpin/infergo/src/v0.7.0/&#34;&gt;out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This release is a result of improving and extending Infergo
along with development of &lt;a href=&#34;http://infergo.org/piers/gogp&#34;&gt;GoGP&lt;/a&gt;,
a library for Gaussian process regression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s new:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;model&amp;rsquo;s gradient can be explicitly specified as the
&lt;code&gt;Gradient()&lt;/code&gt; method, instead of through automatic
differentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An elemental may also be a function which accepts a slice of
floats (in addition to functions which accept one or more
float scalars as parameters).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More kernels in the supplied kernel library.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As usual, fixes and performance improvements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>infergo v0.6.1</title>
      <link>http://infergo.org/news/v0.6.1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2019 10:56:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://infergo.org/news/v0.6.1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Infergo v0.6.1 is &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/dtolpin/infergo/src/v0.6.1/&#34;&gt;out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s new:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I moved many things around, some in a backward-incompatible way, but should
only affect a minority of users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a side-effect of using Infergo for a rather involved model, I fixed two
bugs in the automatic differentiation transformation. The bugs manifested
in edge cases I didn&amp;rsquo;t even think they exist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The accompanying repository
&lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/dtolpin/infergo-studies&#34;&gt;infergo-studies&lt;/a&gt;
now contains a new case study &amp;mdash; a rewrite of Stan&amp;rsquo;s LDA
example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>infergo v0.5.0</title>
      <link>http://infergo.org/news/v0.5.0/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 19:45:20 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://infergo.org/news/v0.5.0/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;infergo v0.5.0&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/dtolpin/infergo/src/v0.5.0/&#34;&gt;out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s new:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multithreading support. Differentiation can be performed concurrently in
multiple goroutines without locking of calls to Observe or Gradient,
and with little contention.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examples and case studies performing inference in parallel, both using
Infergo&amp;rsquo;s own inference algorithms, or through integration in Gonum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Tale of GoIDs</title>
      <link>http://infergo.org/news/tale-of-goids/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 15:19:22 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://infergo.org/news/tale-of-goids/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.16&lt;/strong&gt; And the LORD God commanded the man, saying: &amp;lsquo;Of every tree of the garden
thou mayest freely eat;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.17&lt;/strong&gt; but of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil,
thou shalt not eat of it; for in the day that thou eatest thereof thou shalt
surely die.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Book of Genesis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://golang.org/&#34;&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt; gives the programmer introspection into every aspect
of &lt;a href=&#34;https://godoc.org/reflect&#34;&gt;the language&lt;/a&gt;, and of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://godoc.org/runtime&#34;&gt;running
program&lt;/a&gt;. But to one thing the programmer does not
have access, and it is the goroutine identifier. Because the day the
programmers know the goroutine identifier, they create goroutine-local storage
through shared access and mutexes, and shall surely die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;However,&lt;/strong&gt; there are use cases beyond concurrent &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.golang.org/context&#34;&gt;handling of HTTP
requests&lt;/a&gt;, in which
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.golang.org/share-memory-by-communicating&#34;&gt;sharing memory by
communicating&lt;/a&gt;
through channels or passing the context around is not going to
work. One such case is &lt;a href=&#34;http://infergo.org/&#34;&gt;Infergo&lt;/a&gt;.  Infergo
transforms Go source code to enable &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Automatic_differentiation#Reverse_accumulation&#34;&gt;reverse-mode automatic
differentiation&lt;/a&gt;.
Function &lt;em&gt;signatures&lt;/em&gt; stay unchanged, but function &lt;em&gt;bodies&lt;/em&gt; are
modified to write to a so-called &lt;em&gt;tape&lt;/em&gt; a trace of every
floating point operation. A single tape must be accessible by
all functions. If derivatives are computed concurrently in
multiple goroutines, every goroutine must have its own tape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The functions must know how to get to the tape. And getting to
the tape must be very efficient: every floating point operation
involves an access to the tape!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not that no one thought about goroutine identifiers
before. There are Go programmers who need the identifiers, some
of them admit the need, and a few find workarounds to actually
obtain the identifiers.  I searched for the workarounds, I found
several worthy attempts, and then I had a revelation, and then I
discovered someone who had the same revelation before me. And
that gave Infergo efficient goroutine-local storage for
concurrent automatic differentiation and inference. Here is how
it went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;worthy-attempts&#34;&gt;Worthy Attempts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;from-the-makers-of-go&#34;&gt;From the makers of Go&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bradfitz.com/&#34;&gt;Brad Fitzpatrick&lt;/a&gt; is a member of the Go
programming language team at Google. Brad wrote a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bradfitz/http2/blob/master/gotrack.go&#34;&gt;function&lt;/a&gt;
which obtains the goroutine identifier. The function creates a
stack trace and parses the identifier out of string
representation of the trace. Brad needed this for debugging, &amp;ldquo;to
track that functions run on the goroutine  that they&amp;rsquo;re supposed
to&amp;rdquo;. The function uses public API calls and an undocumented but
stable format of the serialized stack trace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhat cumbersome but working. Unfortunately, too inefficient
for Infergo use case. Collecting, serializing, and parsing the
stack trace on every operation makes automatic differentiation
2,000 (&lt;strong&gt;two thousand&lt;/strong&gt;) times slower!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;from-the-users-of-go&#34;&gt;From the users of Go&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://jtolio.com/&#34;&gt;JT Olio&lt;/a&gt; wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jtolds/gls&#34;&gt;goroutine-local storage
library&lt;/a&gt;. The library &amp;ldquo;defines 16
special functions and embed base-16 tags into the stack using
the call order of those 16 functions.&amp;rdquo; Then, this embedding is
used to produce an unique goroutine identifier and establish
goroutine-local storage. The idea blew me away! However, the
library requires that Go routines are created through a library
call.  I could modify Infergo&amp;rsquo;s own inference algorithms, however I
would not be able to pass functions and gradients to third-party
code. Infergo
&lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/dtolpin/infergo-studies/src/master/lr-gonum/&#34;&gt;integrates&lt;/a&gt;
with &lt;a href=&#34;http://gonum.org/&#34;&gt;Gonum&lt;/a&gt; optimization nicely, and by
enabling goroutine-local tapes I strived to improve this
integration, rather than sacrifice it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;revelation&#34;&gt;Revelation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was almost ready to give up, that is, to write code that
adds an extra &amp;lsquo;context&amp;rsquo; parameter to every differentiated function.
But then it came down onto me that maybe Go does not want to
prevent me from using the goroutine identifier.  Maybe it is
there, and I just do not see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, Go has an &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/doc/asm&#34;&gt;assembly
language&lt;/a&gt;. The language is
documented, Go functions can be implemented in Go assembly.  If
I wanted a system feature not available through a library, I
would write an assembly function bringing that feature to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same goes for Go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only Go has an assembler, the assembler has a dedicated
register &lt;code&gt;g&lt;/code&gt; pointing at &lt;code&gt;runtime.g&lt;/code&gt;, the goroutine descriptor.
&lt;code&gt;goid&lt;/code&gt;, the Go routine identifier is just one of the fields of
the descriptor. I can just use the contents of &lt;code&gt;g&lt;/code&gt; to get
the goroutine identifier, and it will only be a couple
instructions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is much easier to find something if you know what you are
looking for. &lt;a href=&#34;https://zhuanlan.zhihu.com/taowen&#34;&gt;Tao Wen&lt;/a&gt; wrote
yet another &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/modern-go/gls&#34;&gt;GLS library&lt;/a&gt;; and
this library does exactly what I just described: uses Go
assembler to access register &lt;code&gt;g&lt;/code&gt;, and retrieves field &lt;code&gt;goid&lt;/code&gt;
from the structure pointed to by the register. I somewhat
simplified the code, added support for all platforms where
Go is available, and now Infergo has fast and straightforward
support for multithreading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned&#34;&gt;Lessons Learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is sometimes easier to find a hole in the fence than to
jump over.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can do anything with Go. You just must prove (to yourself
more than to others) that you are brave and skilled enough.
For example, by diving into Go internals and coding in Go
assembly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;My Samsung Tab S4 tablet is amazingly well fit for
multithreading, in Go in particular. I did most of the
development on the tablet, in &lt;a href=&#34;https://termux.com&#34;&gt;Termux&lt;/a&gt;.
The tablet&amp;rsquo;s CPU  has 8 cores, and Go runs multiple
goroutines in parallel with very little overhead: 8 inference
threads in parallel take roughly the same time as a single
thread with local goroutine storage, and only 20% slower than
a single thread with a global tape, for the same amount of
computation per thread.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can run &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/dtolpin/infergo-studies/src/master/wasm/&#34;&gt;multiple goroutines in parallel in a
browser&lt;/a&gt; via
WebAssembly. WebAssembly is slower than other targets, but
still quite fast.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>infergo v0.3.0</title>
      <link>http://infergo.org/news/v0.3.0/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2019 02:04:30 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://infergo.org/news/v0.3.0/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;infergo v0.3.0&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/dtolpin/infergo/src/v0.3.0/&#34;&gt;out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s new:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only methods returning float64 or nothing are differentiated. This allows
to define helper methods on the model, such as returning the number of
parameters, and call the methods outside of differentiated context.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;infergo&lt;/code&gt; models can be optimized using &lt;a href=&#34;https://godoc.org/gonum.org/v1/gonum/optimize&#34;&gt;Gonum optimization
algorithms&lt;/a&gt;. This includes
BFGS and variants. Case study
&lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/dtolpin/infergo-studies/src/master/lr-gonum/&#34;&gt;lr-gonum&lt;/a&gt;
applies L-BFGS to linear regression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/dtolpin/infergo-studies&#34;&gt;Case studies&lt;/a&gt; have been extended. New
studies include:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;linear regression, solved using either stochastic gradient descent and BFGS;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;compilation of &lt;code&gt;infergo&lt;/code&gt; models and inference into WebAssembly and running in
the browser;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;integration with Gonum;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neal&amp;rsquo;s funnel, a re-parameterization example borrowed from &lt;a href=&#34;https://mc-stan.org/users/documentation/&#34;&gt;Stan documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>infergo v0.2.2</title>
      <link>http://infergo.org/news/v0.2.2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2018 01:14:30 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://infergo.org/news/v0.2.2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;infergo v0.2.2&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/dtolpin/infergo/src/v0.2.2/&#34;&gt;out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s new:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Constant folding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automatic import of packages required for short variable declarations
(see &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/dtolpin/infergo/issues/10&#34;&gt;issue #10&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>infergo v0.2.1</title>
      <link>http://infergo.org/news/v0.2.1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Nov 2018 16:19:03 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://infergo.org/news/v0.2.1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;infergo v0.2.1&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/dtolpin/infergo/src/v0.2.1/&#34;&gt;out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s new:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://infergo.org&#34;&gt;infergo.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why infergo</title>
      <link>http://infergo.org/news/why/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Nov 2018 14:19:13 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://infergo.org/news/why/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I share here my experiences from integrating probabilistic
programming into a server-side software system and
implementing a  probabilistic programming facility for Go, a
modern programming language of choice for server-side software
development.  Server-side application of probabilistic
programming poses challenges for a probabilistic programming
system. I discuss the challenges and my experience in
overcoming them, and suggest guidelines that can help in a
wider adoption of probabilistic programming in server-side
software systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;challenges-of-server-side-probabilistic-programming&#34;&gt;Challenges of Server-Side Probabilistic Programming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incorporating a probabilistic program, or rather a probabilistic
procedure, within a larger code body appears to be rather
straightforward: one implements the model in the probabilistic
programming language, fetches and preprocesses the data in the
host programming language, passes the data and the model to an
inference algorithm, and post-processes the results in the
host programming language again to make algorithmic
decisions based on inference outcomes. However, complex
server-side software systems make integration of probabilistic
inference challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;simulation-vs-inference&#34;&gt;Simulation vs. inference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probabilistic models often follow a design pattern of
simulation-inference: a significant part of the model is a
simulator, running an algorithm with fixed parameters; the
optimal parameters, or their distribution, are to be inferred.
The inferred parameters are then used by the software system to
execute the simulation independently of inference for
forecasting and decision making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pattern suggests re-use of the simulator: instead of
implementing the simulator twice, in the probabilistic model and
in the host environment, the same code can serve both purposes.
However to achieve this, the host language must coincide with
the implementation language of the probabilistic model, on one
hand, and allow a computationally efficient implementation of
the simulation, on the other hand. Some probabilistic systems
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cra.com/work/case-studies/figaro&#34;&gt;Figaro&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://anglican.ml/&#34;&gt;Anglican&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://turing.ml/&#34;&gt;Turing&lt;/a&gt;)
are built with tight integration with the host environment in
mind; more often than not though the probabilistic code is
not trivial to re-use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-interface&#34;&gt;Data interface&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a server-side application data for inference comes from a
variety of sources: network, databases, distributed file
systems, and in many different formats. Efficient inference
depends on fast data access and updating. Libraries for data
access and manipulation are available in the host environment.
While the host environment can be used as a proxy retrieving and
transforming the data, such as in the case of &lt;a href=&#34;http://mc-stan.org/&#34;&gt;Stan&lt;/a&gt;
integrations, sometimes direct access from the probabilistic
code is the preferred option, for example when the data is
streamed or retrieved conditionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;integration-and-deployment&#34;&gt;Integration and deployment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deployment of server-side software systems is a delicate process
involving automatic builds and maintenance of dependencies.
Adding  a component, which possibly introduces additional
software dependencies or even a separate runtime, complicates
deployment. Minimizing the burden of probabilistic programming
on the integration and deployment process should be a major
consideration in design or selection of probabilistic
programming tools.  Probabilistic programming systems that are
implemented or provide an interface in a popular programming
language, e.g.  Python (&lt;a href=&#34;http://edwardlib.org/&#34;&gt;Edward&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://pyro.ai/&#34;&gt;Pyro&lt;/a&gt;) are easier to integrate and deploy, however
the smaller the footprint of a probabilistic system, the easier
is the adoption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;probabilistic-programming-facility-for-go&#34;&gt;Probabilistic Programming Facility for Go&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the experience of developing and deploying solutions
using different probabilistic environments, I propose
guidelines to implementation of a probabilistic programming
facility for server-side applications. I believe that these
guidelines, when followed, help easier integration of
probabilistic programming inference into large-scale server-side
software systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A probabilistic model should be programmed in the host
programming language. The facility may impose a discipline on
model implementation, such as through interface constraints, but
otherwise supporting unrestricted use of the host language for
implementation of the model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Built-in and user-defined data structures and libraries
should be accessible in the probabilistic programming model.
Inference techniques relying on the code structure, such as
those based on automatic differentiation, should support the
use of common data structures of the host language.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The model code should be reusable between inference and
simulation. The code which is not required solely for inference
should be written once for both inference of parameters and use
of the parameters in the host environment.  It should be
possible to run simulation outside the probabilistic model without
runtime or memory overhead imposed by inference needs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In line with the guidelines, I have implemented a probabilistic
programming facility for the Go programming language, &lt;code&gt;infergo&lt;/code&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;http://infergo.org/&#34;&gt;http://infergo.org/&lt;/a&gt;). I have chosen Go
because Go is a small but expressive programming language with
efficient implementation, which has recently become quite
popular for computation-intensive server-side programming.  This
facility is already used in production environment for inference
of mission-critical algorithm parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A probabilistic model in &lt;code&gt;infergo&lt;/code&gt; is an implementation
of the &lt;code&gt;Model&lt;/code&gt; interface requiring a single method
&lt;code&gt;Observe&lt;/code&gt; which accepts a vector (a Go &lt;em&gt;slice&lt;/em&gt;) of
floats, the parameters to infer, and returns a single float,
interpreted as unnormalized log-likelihood of the posterior
distribution. Implementation of model methods can be written
in virtually unrestricted Go and use any Go libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For inference, &lt;code&gt;infergo&lt;/code&gt; relies on automatic
differentiation. The source code of the model is
translated by a command-line tool provided by &lt;code&gt;infergo&lt;/code&gt;
into an equivalent model with reverse-mode automatic
differentiation of the log-likelihood with respect
to the parameters applied. The differentiation operates
on the built-in floating-point type and incurs only a small
computational overhead. However, even this overhead is avoided
when the model code is executed outside of inference algorithms:
both the original and the differentiated model are
simultaneously available to the rest of the program code, so
the methods can be called on the differentiated model for
inference, and on the original model for the most efficient
execution with the inferred parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Go programming language and development environment offer
capabilities which made implementation of &lt;code&gt;infergo&lt;/code&gt;
affordable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Go parser and abstract syntax tree serializer are
a part of the standard library. Parsing, transforming,
and generating Go source code is straightforward and
effortless.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Type inference (or &lt;em&gt;type checking&lt;/em&gt; as it is
called in the Go ecosystem), also provided in the
standard library, augments parsing and allows to
selectively apply transformation-based automatic
differentiation  based on static expression types.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go compiles and runs fast. Fast compilation and
execution speeds allow to use the same facility for both
exploratory design of probabilistic models and for
inference in production environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go offers efficient parallel execution as a
first-class feature, via so-called &lt;em&gt;goroutines&lt;/em&gt;.
Goroutines streamline implementation of sampling-based
inference algorithms. Sample generators and consumers
are run in parallel, communicating through channels.
Inference is easy to parallelize in order to exploit
hardware multi-processing, and samples are retrieved
lazily for postprocessing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 1 provides memory consumption and running time
measurements on basic models to illustrate  &lt;code&gt;infergo&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rsquo;s
performance.  The measurements were obtained on a 2.3GHz Intel
Core 5 CPU with 8GB of memory for 1000 iterations of Hamiltonian
Monte Carlo with 10 leapfrog steps. Note that log-likelihood
computation for standard distributions is not optimized yet.
Quite the opposite: since models in &lt;code&gt;infergo&lt;/code&gt; are fully
composable, primitive distributions are themselves implemented
as &lt;code&gt;infergo&lt;/code&gt; models and automatically differentiated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Table 1: Memory and running times for 1000 iterations of HMC with 10 leapfrog steps.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;model&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;compilation time&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;execution time&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;memory&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8 schools&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.15s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.6s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.5MB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10D normal, 100 points&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.15s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.0s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.7MB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;50D normal, 100 points&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.15s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.0s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.8MB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lightweight probabilistic programming facility similar to
&lt;code&gt;infergo&lt;/code&gt; can be added to most modern general-purpose
programming languages, in particular those used in implementing
large-scale software systems, making probabilistic
programming inference more accessible in server-side
applications.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
